(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-08-01T04:59:56.918654",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
しくじりかなたそ
Kanataso's School of Blunders—
僕みたいになるな！
don't end up like me!
しくじりかなたそ ぼくみたいになるな！！
[Kanataso's School of Blunders: Don't Be Like Me!!]
はーい、ということで、こん……今回、教員を務める天音かなたです！
Hello! Today, Amane Kanata
よろしくお願いします！
will be your teacher!
よろしくおねがいしまーす！
Nice to meet you!
それでは生徒の皆様の自己紹介を！
Now, let's have the students introduce themselves!
はーい！もぐもぐおかゆ！ホロライブゲーマーズの
Hi! Mogu Mogu Okayu!
猫又おかゆです！よろしくお願いします、先生！
I'm Nekomata Okayu from Hololive Gamers!
そして、らみっちょ！
And Ramiccho!
はーい！ホロライブ5期生の雪花ラミィです！
Hi! I'm Yukihana Lamy from Hololive 5th Gen!
先生、よろしくお願いします！
Nice to meet you, teacher!
そして、りりかちゃん！
And Ririka-chan!
はーい！先生、可愛いポジティブジニアス！
Hi! Teacher, I'm the cute positive genius,
ホロライブデヴァイスのしくじり担当？一条莉々華でーす！
Hololive DEV_IS's blunder rep, Ichijou Ririka!
そんなことない、全然、大丈夫大丈夫、そんなことない全然。
That's not true, you're totally fine!
本当に皆さん、お忙しい中集まっていただきありがとうございます。
Thank you all so much for gathering here despite your busy schedules.
いやいや、こちらこそ楽しみ！
Not at all, we're looking forward to it!
あの、カニ奢りますから！
Um, I'm treating you to crab!
やったー！カニ奢りますから！カニ奢ってね、
Yay! Since I'm treating you to crab!
あの、お礼とさせていただきますので。
As a thank-you for having you all.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
はい。
Yes.
ということでね、あの、今日はですね、もう本当に、あの、天音かなた、僕がね、しくじってしまった、やってしまった過去のしくじりをとにかくたくさん話していって、
So today, I, Amane Kanata, am going
to talk at length about my past blunders,
みんな同じことを繰り返さぬようにと、いうね、これからの活動の参考にしてもらえたらというようなものでして、
so that everyone won't repeat them,
and use it as a reference for your future activities.
じゃあちょっと、さっそくなんですが、僕のしくじりについて授業を始めたいと思います！はい！
Now, without further ado, let's start the lesson on my blunders! Yes!
それではですね、皆さん、おお手元にあります教科書の1ページ目を開いてください。
Now then, everyone, please open to page 1 of the textbook in front of you.
はい！
Yes!
授業テーマ「デビュー直後のキャラ迷走！天音かなたのしくじり人生」
[Lesson Theme: Character Identity Crisis Right After Debut! Amane Kanata's Life of Blunders]
そんなことあったっけ？
Was there really something like that?
あったんですね、実は。
There was, actually.
じゃあ、まずはデビュー直後の天音かなたのホロライブ人生のあの、上がり下がりをね、グラフにしてみました。
Well, first, I graphed the ups and downs of Amane Kanata's Hololive life right after debut.
次のページ。
Next page.
下がってるねー！下がってる！こんなにー！
It's going down! It went down! So much!
まあそうですね、やっぱりデビューが100だとしたら、だんだん下がっていって50%、
Well, that's right. If debut was 100,
it gradually dropped to 50%,
まだ1年経たないうちに、なんか20%とかそのへんに、どんどん……
and in less than a year, down to 20%
or so, steadily...
何があったんですかね。
Something happened, huh?
すご、そんな何があったんですか？
Wait, what actually happened?
いや、ちょっと何があったのか解説していきたいと思います。
I'd like to explain what went down.
僕は2019年12月27日、約5年前ですね、デビューしたんですけれども、
I debuted about five years ago on December 27, 2019,
デビュー前、「これから楽しいホロライブ生活が始まるんだ！」と
thinking, "My wonderful Hololive life is finally beginning!"
期待に胸を大きく大きく膨らませていました。
my expectations were so high.
待って待って？
Wait, wait?
そんな平らなのに？
With that flat chest?
ちょっと、
Wait—
膨らみすぎて破裂しちゃっただけですもんね。
She just inflated too much and exploded, right?
いやまだ膨らみ続けているという感じなんですが。
Well, it's more like she's still keeping on inflating.
そうなんだ。
That's right.
デビュー前は、あの憧れの先輩たち一人一人に全部違う文章で連絡をしました。
Before my debut, I contacted all my admired seniors with completely different messages.
連絡くれた、くれてた！
They replied!
おかゆちゃんにも潜りましたし、頑張ってデビュー配信の資料を作ったりもしてて。
I even slid into Okayu-chan's DMs and worked hard on my debut stream materials.
資料は？
Materials?
そうなんです。え、みんなデビュー前ってどんな感じでした？
So, everyone, what was it like before your debut?
え、茉莉華ほんとまだ直近じゃないですか？
Ririka, yours was really recent, wasn't it?
そうそう、そうそう。
Yeah, exactly.
偉大なる先輩たちの配信をいっぱい見て研究して、もう3か月～4か月かけてデビュー配信の準備しました。
I watched streams of my great seniors to study, and spent 3 to 4 months preparing for my debut stream.
すごい！
Amazing!
めちゃすごい！
Awesome!
いや、ラミィもデビューするまでは何か月もかけて、デビュー初配信の準備してた。
Lamy also spent several months preparing for her debut stream.
おかゆは？
What about you, Okayu?
ぼくん時はその準備とかないからさ。
When I debuted, there wasn't really any preparation like that.
あー。
Ah, I see.
全然もう。
Not at all.
ま、多少ね、1時間もたせるためのちょっとした工夫はありましたけど、
Well, I did put in a little effort to fill a whole hour,
今の子達の初配信とはもう全然クオリティの差がハンパなかったですよ。
but the quality of today's rookies' debut streams is on a totally different level!
あー。
I see.
そうなんだ。
Right?
確かにどんどんね、やっぱり初配信ってクオリティが上がっていって、いきなりオリジナル曲があるとかオープニングにアニメーションがあるとか、あったと思うんですけど。
First debuts keep getting higher in quality, with original songs or opening animations right off the bat, right?
その大事な初配信ではこんなしくじりをしました。次のページ。
During such important debut streams, we made some major blunders. Let's look at the next page.
えっ、なんだこれ。
Huh?
視聴者の意見は「クソダサイ」
Viewer's opinion: "THAT SUCKS!"
あったあった～！
It was, it was!
本当一生懸命。
We worked so hard!
本当1ヶ月以上かけて作ったパワーポイントの資料が酷評されてしまいまして。
The PowerPoint presentation I spent over a month making was slated as terrible and bombed.
あの、そんな僕の初配信の映像がございますので見てほしいです。映像がこちら！
Well, we have footage of my debut stream, so please take a look. Here is the footage!
ようこそ…
Welcome...
何だこれ。
Wait, what's that?
今のクソダサの初配信じゃん。
Wait, is that the "That Sucks" debut stream?
マジでにしてきた。大事件だよ、アニメーション。
Yeah, it really is! It's a big deal, that animation!
星マークえぐ。
Star mark is fierce.
はい。
Yeah.
謎の写真。
Mysterious photo.
なんだこの寿司。
What is this sushi?
自己紹介していきたいと思います。
Let me introduce myself.
面白そう。
So funny.
明日から出てきた？
Wait, it's coming from tomorrow?
読み にく 天音かなたです。
Nice to meet you, I'm Kanata Amane.
夢や目標。
Dreams and goals.
収益化を目指す！！
Monetization!
ニコちゃんマークも出してね。
Also a smiley face mark.
登録者数 5万人！
50,000 subscribers!
これをね、皆さんホロライブ好きな方分かると思うんですけど
I'm sure you all love Hololive, so you probably get it, but
まず、あの、3D化したいってことで、5万人まず目指そうっていうとこですね。
first, I want to become 3D, so I'm aiming for 50,000 subscribers as a start!
ライブに出演してコールアンドレスポンスをやりたい。
I want to perform at a live concert and do call-and-response!
あれね、ちょっとね、夢ですね。
That's, uh, quite a dream.
今のパワーポイントの準備に1か月ガチでかけてます。
I spent a solid month preparing for that PowerPoint.
ヤバすぎる！
Too crazy!
すごい言われましたね、同期にもその1か月他のことできただろうとか、
People told me, "You could've done other things with that month,"
色々言われたんですけど、ちょっと皆さんどうでしたか？おしゃれでした？
various things, but how did you guys find it? Was it stylish?
正直に、正直に莉々華どうだった？
Ririka, be honest, what did you think?
くっそダサいです！
It's so damn lame!
ダサい！
So lame!
やっぱダサい？
Still lame?
うん。
Yeah.
それがかなたんの良さだよね。
Well, that's Kanatan's charm, right?
ちょっとダサい。
A little lame.
ちょっとダサい。個性はあったよね。
A little lame, but it had personality.
あったね。PP天使とか言われてたしね。
It did. People called you PP Angel and stuff.
未だに海外ニキはPPエンジェルって言ってくれたりして。
Yeah, overseas fans still call me PP Angel.
Tシャツもありますもんね。
There's even a T-shirt, right?
最初に出したやつね。水色のね。
The one we released first, the light blue one.
いや、そうなんですよ。
Yeah, exactly.
しかもデビュー配信では他にも全部自分の声で演奏から作ったソーラン節を流したりと、尖ったデビュー配信をね、やっぱしてはおりましたが、
And during my debut stream, I also played a Soran Bushi cover made entirely with my own voice, and did all sorts of edgy things.
ソーラン節ってなんですか？
What on earth is a Soran Bushi?
ソーラン節ね。
Soran Bushi, yeah.
見たいですか？
Wanna see it?
見たい！！見たい見たい！
I wanna see it! I wanna see it!
映像があるのでご覧ください。
We have the footage, so please take a look.
ヤーレン ソーラン…
Yaren, Soran...
ソーラン ソーラン…
Soran, Soran...
(ドッコイショドッコイショ！！)
(Ha, dokkoisho, dokkoisho!)
ソーラン ソーラン…
Soran, Soran...
(ドッコイショドッコイショ！！)
(Ha, dokkoisho, dokkoisho!)
ヤーレン ソーラン…
Yaren, Soran...
ソーラン ソーラン…
Soran, Soran...
(ドッコイショドッコイショ！！)
(Ha, dokkoisho, dokkoisho!)
エコークかかってる。
Echoes are kicking in!
ポボポボのエコーかかってますね。
Pobopobo's echoes are kicking in!
一応こう右側を見ていただくと、みんなドッコイショドッコイショって一応言ってくれてる。
If you look at the right side, everyone's saying "dokkoisho."
これ最後のドヤ顔ね。
This is the final flex.
ぴゅ～～
Phew~
やかんやん。
A kettle!
やかん。
こんな配信をしてますがね、実は初めはクールキャラで行こうと考えて、
We've been doing streams like that, but actually, at first, I thought about going with a cool character.
これです？
With this?!
そう
Right.
やっぱり参考にしてたのは
Actually, I was taking...
おかゆ先輩
...Okayu-senpai as reference.
わぁー！
Wow!
これわ本当に出会っちゃったが
This is really...
いや、ありがたいね。ね？
Yeah, really.
いや、いや、もう本当に出会いなんだけど。
まあ、クールぶっていたけど、なんかダサいらしい
Well, I tried to act cool, but...
パワーポイントを駆使してね、
...using some uncool PowerPoint...
今後の迷走を予感させる配信となってしまいました。
...it turned into a stream that foreshadowed future wandering.
でも、みんなも初配信はあるということで、
Everyone has a debut stream, too.
皆さん、どうですか？自分の初配信、覚えてますか？おかゆ先輩！
Everyone, how about it? Do you remember your debut stream, Okayu-senpai?
覚えてますよ。
I remember.
おっ。
Ohh.
まあ、若かった。
Well, I was young.
いや、今も若いですよ！
You're still young now!
いや、若い。
Yeah, I was young.
もう7年目かな？今。
Is it already my 7th year, I wonder?
7年の経つと思うと、まあそれはね、確かに時間が経って大人になっているか、
Thinking about it being 7 years, it makes me feel like time has passed and I've grown up.
うん、それは感じるかな。
I feel that way.
そう、デビュー配信もね、僕も終わり、
Right, my debut stream, too...
ダサいと言われつつも、1週間後に、あの、先ほど夢でね、掲げました、登録者5万を達成し、
...even though people called it uncool, one week after debut I achieved my dream of 50,000 subscribers,
素晴らしい！
That's wonderful!
出だしは非常に順調だったんですが、
And the start was going very smoothly, but...
こういう気持ちを抱くようになります。次のページ。
...I started to hold these kinds of feelings. Next page, please.
プレッシャーだな…
Such pressure...
わかる〜。
I get it~.
プレッシャーだ…
Such pressure...
やっぱり、あの、ホロライブというところに所属させていただいたことによる、あのリスナーさん数字とかってあったのね。特に、そのデビューして何もしてないから、いいのかな？これでっていうのを、感じたりしましたね。
You see, because I belonged to a place called hololive, there were things like listener numbers, right? Especially since I hadn't done anything since debut, I felt like, "Is this okay?"
皆さんはこうデビューしたての時ってどうでしたか？
How was it for everyone right after your debut?
ラミーは、もう、それこそ4期生が盛り上がってるところでデビューをしたので、
Lamy was... well, right when the 4th generation was getting hyped up, I debuted, so...
そうだね。
Right, right.
プレッシャーもすごかったし、結構批判的な意見も多かった。
...the pressure was immense, and there were quite a few critical opinions.
えっ、そうなんだ。
Eh?
どんな？
Like what?
いやもう、あの、「ゴキブリの5期生」とか。えぇ〜っ！！
Like, "The cockroaches of the 5th gen," and things like that.
ひどいよ。すごいね。結構、才能なしみたいな。
Terrible. They called us totally talentless.
すごい言われましたよ。
I got told some crazy things.
でもやっぱりこう、先輩が築き上げてきたものに乗っかってる感じだったのね。
But still, since it felt like we were riding on what our seniors had built up,
なんか気持ちはわかる。そう、プレッシャーがね、すごかった。
I can totally understand that feeling. The pressure was huge.
ええっ！
Eh?
うん。
Hmm.
おかゆ先輩あった、プレッシャー？
Did you have pressure, Okayu-senpai?
いや、僕が入った時は、もうそんなね、まだまだ人も少なくって、もう、大空スバル選手権の前日に、大空スバルのモノマネの練習をするだけで1時間枠取ったりして。
Well, when I joined, there weren't many people yet, and the day before the "Oozora Subaru Championship", just practicing Oozora Subaru's impressions took up a whole hour-long slot!
プレッシャー感じなくていいから、マジで。
You really didn't need to feel pressure, seriously!
いいな、古き良きホロライブを感じますね。
I feel that good, old-time hololive vibe.
そんなこともありますよ。
Things like that happen, too.
いや、そうだね。
Yeah, that's true.
うん、僕もね、やっぱりデビュー直後だったんで、特にね、先輩たちにもなんか恩返ししたいとか、リスナーさんにも何かとか、そういうことをね、すごく考えていました。
And since I was right after my debut, I really thought a lot about wanting to give back to the seniors and wanting to do something for the listeners, too.
そしてこの考えが悪い方に働いてしまい、その結果僕はこうなってしまいます。次のページ！
And this mindset worked against me, and as a result, I ended up like this. Next page!
デビュー直後のキャラ迷走、気合いが完全に空回りしていた、暗期の「初期かなた」時代！
Character derailment right after debut. Enthusiasm totally backfiring. The dark "Early Kanata" era!
暗闇ですか？
Darkness?!
暗黒…
Darkness...
いや、もうとんでもない暗黒の時代でした。
It was a truly unbelievable dark era.
初期かなた、まあどんな感じだったのか、デビュー当時の状況を説明しますと、当時はARKというゲームが大流行してましてね。
To explain the situation when I was "Early Kanata," back then the game ARK was all the rage.
みんなやってたもんね。
Everyone was playing it!
僕はゲームに慣れていなかったんで、
I wasn't used to games...
まあゲームもタジタジしつつ、コラボもしたり、喋りもいっぱい頑張って、でもコメントも拾わなきゃと、全部やろうとしたら、
...so while struggling with the game, I tried to do everything at once—collaborate, talk, and also catch chat comments...
先輩が喋ってるのにコメントを読んだりとか、空気が読めていない「初期かなた」が誕生してしまったと。
...giving rise to the "Early Kanata" who read comments while her senior was talking and couldn't read the room at all.
本当にね。
Really...
もうがむしゃら過ぎて、焦りから異常に空気が読めてないのに、無駄に積極的に話しかけてくる、だる絡みの初期かなた。
Out of sheer panic, I was failing to read the room terribly, yet needlessly trying hard to reach out—that was the clingy "Early Kanata."
これね、結構ね、見てたんだけども、
I watched that back then, and...
まあ、ちょっと苦しくなる。胸がキュッてなる。
...it gets a bit painful. My chest gets a tight squeeze.
ちょっとあの共感性羞恥と、あの「あ、この子」っていうその悪意がないのは多分伝わるので、キュッとなる系ではありますね。
With that shared embarrassment, and the "good kid" aspect, I think the lack of malice does come across, so it's the kind of thing that makes your heart squeeze.
頑張ろうと頑張ってしてた感じが。
You could tell she was trying her best.
おかゆ先輩、あの初期かなた時代の僕って覚えてますか？
Okayu-senpai, do you remember me during the "Early Kanata" era?
いや、僕実は、ARKって1回ぐらいしか参加してないから。
Well, actually, I only participated in ARK about once.
だから配信中のかなたんより、配信してないかなたんと関わる方が多かったんです。
So, I interacted more with Kanatan when she wasn't streaming than when she was.
あー、なるほど、なるほど！
Oh, I see, I see!
そう、だから配信してないかなたんは今とあんまり変わんないと思う。
So, I think Kanatan when she's not streaming hasn't changed much from now.
ええっ。
Eh?
そうなんです。実は配信外では普通だったので、
That's right, offstream she was normal, so...
あの、なんでこの配信中はこんなおかしくて、裏では普通に話せるのに「あなたなんでなの？」っていうのを、実はホロメンに言われたこともありました。
...holomem members would actually ask me, "Why are you acting so weird during your streams when you can talk normally behind the scenes?"
ええっ！？
Eh?
「なんでそんなおかしくなっちゃうの？」っていうのね。
Like, "Why do you get so weird?"
まあでもその初期かなたを見たリスナーの反応と言うと、
And as for the reaction of listeners who saw that "Early Kanata"...
怖いよ。
Oh boy.
次のページ！
Next page!
「推しに絡まないで欲しい」「早く辞めろ」
"Don't get involved with my oshi!" "Hurry up and quit!"
いやね、
Well...
もちろん応援してくれる人もたくさんいたんですけど、実はこれ、あの配信開始をする前、待機所の状態でコメントが大荒れしたこともあって、
Of course there were many people who supported me, but actually... before the stream even started, in the waiting room, the comments would sometimes get completely out of hand.
本当に、うん。
Really...
500人ぐらいの人がず〜っと言い合いをする音もあるほど、やっぱりリスナーさんから嫌われてる時期がありましたね。
At one point, with around 500 people constantly arguing, there was a period when I was disliked by listeners.
ああ、そうなんだ。
Oh, is that so?
今じゃ考えられないけど。
You wouldn't think so now, though.
いやいやそんなことないんですけど、これ具体的にね、どんな感じだったかと言いますと、
No, no, it's not like that, but specifically, if I were to describe what it was like...
初期かなたのしじり！コラボの流れをぶった斬ってコメント読み、面白いこと言おうとして滑りまくる、コラボ相手のオウム返しをしてしまう。
Kanata's early blunder! Cutting off collab flow to read comments, bombing while trying to be funny, and echoing the collab partner.
オウム返しとかね、結構多かった。
Echoing and things like that were pretty frequent.
まあオウム返しもね、焦りから何か言わなきゃ、沈黙を作らないようにっていうのが、多分焦りすぎて悪循環になってしまったと。
Well, with echoing too, out of impatience thinking "I must say something, mustn't create silence," it became a vicious cycle.
これはもう初期かなた、本当に大きなしくじりなんですが、
That was a really big blunder for early Kanata.
みんなは新人時代の自分を振り返ってどうですか？ありますか？
How about everyone looking back at your own rookie days? Anything like that?
ううっ…震えてる。
Ugh... I'm shaking.
初期ラミィをいじられるほど初期とキャラが変わってるので、
My character has changed so much from the early days that people can tease early Lamy.
ちょっと昔のラミィを思い出すだけでうっ…ってなるんですけど。
Just remembering the old Lamy makes me go "Ugh..."
やっぱこう、求められる像にならなきゃみたいな。
You feel like you have to become the image people want.
リスナーさんがこんなラミィを求めてるだろうみたいなのに、応えようとしてああっ…てなっていったみたいな。
Trying to live up to what I thought listeners wanted from Lamy, and ending up like that...
hololiveは清浄を求めているみたいなね。
Like, Hololive wants purity.
莉々華はちょっと前のことかもだけど、変わったって思うことある？
Ririka, it might be from a bit ago, but do you feel like you've changed?
いやもう莉々華今も現在進行形で悩まされてて、今お話されてたみたいなことに悩まされてて、もう今帰りないです、帰りたーい！
No, Ririka is still troubled by this currently, just like what we were talking about, I want to go home right now!
ダメだよ！ダメ！
No way! No!
いやでもやっぱ一皮剥きたい！頑張りたいです！
I mean, I want to break out of my shell! I want to try my best!
莉々華めちゃめちゃいいと思いますよ、頑張ってほしいよ。
Ririka, I think you're doing great, I want you to keep trying.
まあこんな感じでね、根は陰キャなのに、頑張って先輩たちに話しかけまくって空回りする僕ば
So like that, even though I'm an introvert at heart, I tried hard to talk to seniors and ended up flailing around.
自分の精神、素の性格とキャラのズレが大きくなっていきます。
The gap between my mental state, true personality and my character grew larger.
そして自分が表でやっていく上でのキャラクターというか、自分の雰囲気に合ったキャラクターっていうものに軌道修正することになりますね。
And so I had to recalibrate my on-stage character to something that fit my actual vibe and personality.
はっちゃけキャラやめようと。
Decided to stop doing the hyper energetic character.
結局ね、やっぱキャラに無理があると精神が削られるんですよね。
In the end, if your character is forced, it really wears down your mental health.
ね？
Right?
分かります！！！とっても分かります！
I know right?! Totally understand!
ちなみにホロメンとうまく絡めなかったとか、配信後に後悔したようなことを経験がある人いますか？
By the way, does anyone have experience where they couldn't interact well with Holomem or regretted something after a stream?
莉々華？ 莉々華めちゃめちゃあるでしょ？ 全然ないですけどね…
Ririka? Ririka, you definitely have plenty, right? Not at all though...
お酒を飲んでね、もうすごい後悔してラミィ先輩にあのDiscordで、あの「本当に申し訳ございませんでした。よろしければまた一緒に遊んでいただけると嬉しいです」ってめちゃめちゃ送って…
I drank alcohol, and had huge regrets, and sent Lamy-senpai a Discord message like, "I am truly, terribly sorry. If you'd be willing to play with me again, I'd be so happy"
ついつい今年の話ですね！こんな前の…
That was just this year! Not long ago at all!
そんなこともあって、ま、僕一時期、気持ちがどん底まで落ち続けしてしまいましたが、迷走しながらも配信を頑張って続けることで、僕にプラスの影響が起きていきます。
So with all that, for a time my feelings hit rock bottom, but by keeping up streams while groping around, positive effects started happening.
次のページ！ 配信を続ける中でキャラが定着！やったー！すごい！
Next page! Character established through continuing streams! Yay! Amazing!
ということでね、長い時間をかけてはいますが、配信の中でできた関係性やホロメンにいじってもらって、いい感じでキャラが定着したりで、自分のことをみんなに知ってもらったりして、配信がだんだんやりやすくなっていきます。
So, it took a long time, but through relationships formed in streams and being teased by Holomem, my character got nicely established, people got to know me, and streaming gradually became easier.
配信で定着した天音かなたのキャラがこちら、次のページ！
Here is Amane Kanata's character established through streams, next page!
配信の中でついたキャラ •センスなしキャラ •握力ゴリラキャラ •ツッコミキャラ
Characters acquired during streams:
• No-sense character • Grip-strength gorilla character • Straight-man character
これぞ今のかなたんだよね。
That's totally Kanatan right now.
センスなしキャラについてはね、僕はちょっと認めてないんですけど、ダサイと言われた代表的なものがたくさんあるんですよう。
Well, about the "no-sense" character, I don't really accept it myself, but there are a lot of representative things people called uncool.
センスなしかなた •PP天使 •洋服がダサイ •#かなたやめろ
Sense-less Kanata:
• PP Angel • Uncool clothes • #StopKanata
PP天使は先ほど紹介しましたが、皆さん僕のセンスなしキャラということで、思い出深い節あったりしますか？
I introduced PP Angel earlier, but do you guys have any memorable moments regarding my sense-less character?
いや〜、ないよね！？ いやでも、あるっちゃあるというか…
No— wait, we don't? Well, but, there is somewhat...
一時期ね、あのかなたの洋服について話し合うDiscordのグループがあったりとかね。
For a time, there was actually a Discord group discussing Kanata's clothes.
ラミィとみお先輩とマリンを集めて突然作って、「あの、僕洋服がダサイって言われるんでおしゃれな洋服（ネットで買える）を教えてください」
I suddenly gathered Lamy, Mio-senpai, and Marine and made a group saying, "Um, people say my clothes are uncool, so please teach me fashionable clothes (that can be bought online)."
外に買いに行かないんだ、ネットで買えるのが大事なんだ。「外に行きたくなかった」っていうセリフがあったりもしましたね、確かに。
You wouldn't go shopping outside, buying online was important. There was even the line "I didn't want to go outside," true.
ちなみにさっき「かなたやめろ」がトレンド入りしたっておっしゃってたと思うんですけど、あれは一体何なんですか？
By the way, earlier you mentioned "#StopKanata" trending, what on earth was that?
これはですね、僕のメンバーシップの名前をつける時の話なんだけど、元々名前の候補が3つありまして、
This is a story from when I was deciding my membership name. Originally there were three candidate names:
•かなたーず •THEかなた •かなたファンクラブ
• Kanata-z • THE Kanata • Kanata Fan Club
これはな… これは、まあ、うん…可愛いよね？
This is... well, um... cute, right?
まあね、こんな感じで候補がありまして、これを見た…
So, we had these candidates, and seeing this...
リスナーさんのね、反応がこちら！
Here is the listeners' reaction!
全部ダサいってすごい ここまで悩むアンケートは初めて
"They're all so lame," "I've never struggled this much with a poll,"
センスが息をしていない
"It has zero sense left."
ボロクソやん！
Absolute trash!
厳しいな。
That's harsh.
悩んでアンケート入れられないと。
"I can't even vote because I'm so torn."
なるほどね。
I see.
ネーミングセンスがダサすぎたということで、この時「#かなたやめろ」のハッシュタグがつけられ、なんと日本のトレンドに入ります。
Because her naming sense was too lame, the hashtag "#KanataStop" was created and actually trended at #2 in Japan!
すごい！
Amazing!
恥ずかしいな。
That's so embarrassing!
おかしいでしょ。でも、どの名前がいいかって当時のTwitterで投票してもらったんですけど、その結果がこうなります。
Right? But here are the results from the Twitter poll back then to see which name was best.
「THE かなた」が選ばれたと。
"THE Kanata" was chosen!
でもなんか全部ほぼ一緒で、みんな悩んでるから。
They're basically all the same, everyone was struggling!
ちょっとね、きみさなの。大接戦の末「THE かなた」に決定したんですよね。
With a very slight difference after a fierce battle, it was decided to be "THE Kanata," right?
悩んだだろうな、これみんな。
They must have struggled a lot, everyone.
みんな悩みましね。
Everyone really struggled, huh?
結局時を経て、去年あたりですかね、「★THE かなた★」がダサいことに私は気づきました。
And eventually, around last year or so, I realized that "THE Kanata" was actually pretty lame.
気づきを得た！
She finally realized it!
いろんなみんながおしゃれな名前だったりとか、ストレートにファンネームをつけているみんなのメンバーシップを見て、「★THE かなた★」ってダサかったんだと思いまして、
Seeing everyone else with stylish names or straightforward fan names for their memberships made me realize how lame "THE Kanata" really was.
現在のメンバーシップの名前は「へい民」になっております。
So now, the membership name is "Heimin" (Commoners).
よかった〜！拍手すんだよよかったじゃない！拍手すんだ！
That's great! You finally managed to clap back!
残念だろ。
What a pity.
でも他にもちょっとかなた先輩といえばで気になってることがあって、
Also, people often talk about Kanata-senpai having certain character traits.
かなた先輩握力キャラというか、力がめちゃあるみたいな感じで、自己紹介とかでも言ってると思うんですけど、
Kanata-senpai is known as a grip-strength gorilla with a lot of physical power, and she talks about it in self-introductions.
あれは最初からではなかったんですか？
Wasn't that a thing from the very beginning?
そうだね、自己紹介で言うようになったのは途中からでね。
That's right, I started mentioning it in my self-introductions midway through.
昔から、本当中学校とかの頃かな、握力が強くて、雑談の中でね握力50kgあったんだよねみたいなことを言ったりとか、
Back in middle school or so, my grip strength was really strong, and I used to casually mention in chats that my grip was 50kg, or things like that.
もうあの、力が強くて物が壊れちゃうって話をよくしてたら、なんかだんだんだんだん、なんかかんないけど「握力ゴリラキャラ」が定着していて。
And as I kept talking about how my strong grip kept breaking things, the "grip-strength gorilla" character somehow naturally stuck.
そんな僕がね、今までうっかり握りつぶしたものは、こちらで。
So, here are the things I've accidentally crushed so far.
多いなあ！
That's a lot!
お寿司、マカロン、蒸したジャガイモ、お弁当のスプーン、コーヒーメーカー、キーボード、Switchのコントローラー、などなどですね。
Sushi, macarons, steamed potatoes, bento spoons, coffee makers, keyboards, Switch controllers, and so on.
お寿司とかマカロンは、マカロン初めて食べた時に、優しく持とうと思ったんだけど、優しく持ったのに、も、ボロボロになって…
For sushi and macarons—when I ate a macaron for the first time, I tried to hold it gently, but even though I tried, it completely crumbled...
そのエピソード大好き！
I love that story!
怖いなあ。
That's terrifying!
あの、この中にあるお弁当のスプーンってやつなんですけど、
As for the bento spoon on that list,
これラミィの企画に前にかなたほうが出してくれた時に、あの楽屋で出るお弁当がカレーだったんだけど、その時のスプーンをバキッて壊しちゃって、普通に食べてるだけでスプーン壊してて。
when Kanata-tan appeared on Lamy's stream before, the bento in the green room happened to be curry, and she snapped the spoon in half just by eating normally!
そうなんです。
Yeah, seriously.
そう、びっくりしましたね。
I was so surprised, seriously!
家ではあれですか、石のすぷーんとか使ってるの？
Do you use stone spoons at home or something?
石のスプーン違いますよ。
No, stone spoons? That's not it!
鉄すら壊す。
I even break metal!
まあ、あのちゃんと割り箸とか使いますけど、たまに割り箸も割れるけど。
I mean, I use disposable chopsticks and stuff, though sometimes those break too.
そうですね、スプーンまっぷたつ事件は楽屋でこれやったのは2回ありますね。
Anyway, that "snapping a spoon in half" incident has happened twice in the green room.
やば〜い！2回もあったんだ！
No way, twice?!
怖い。
That's terrifying.
そしてちょっと前配信の流れで握力を計測した結果がこちらでございます。握力55.9kgですね。ゴリラやん！
And the result of my grip strength test from a recent stream is right here: 55.9kg!
やば！
That's insane!
配信でお酒をね、珍しく飲んだ時に、酔ってリミッター外れてんじゃない？みたいなノリで、
I drank alcohol on stream for once, and feeling a bit tipsy, I thought, "Maybe my limiter is off right now?"
握力計が僕のお家にあるので測ってみたんですけど、55.9kgの新記録が出て、
So I measured it with the grip strength meter I have at home, and I got a new record of 55.9kg.
これはですね、レスリングの霊長類最強女子吉田沙保里さんが、あるテレビ番組で計測したのが55kgだったの
That actually beats Saori Yoshida, the strongest woman in human history, who measured 55kg on a TV show!
おいおいおいおい、それ超えてます！
You beat her?!
ちょっと握手してみますか？
Want to try a handshake?
やだやだ、怖い怖い。
Scary, scary, scary.
ラミィ、ラミィとかね、ラミィとか前に握手したことあるんで、
Lamy, Lamy, you've shaken hands with me before, right?
あ、ね。新人ちゃん。
Ah, right. Ah, newcomer-chan.
え、ていうか、握力7kgだったんですけど…
Wait, your grip strength was 7kg...
じゃあ、1回僕を壊す気で来てください。
Then come at me with the intent to break my hand!
8倍！え、行きますよ。8倍！
8x! Let's go!
オラァ！もっと本気で来い！
Come at me with more spirit!
オラァ！くそっ！あーーーっ！！
Aaaaaah!
う、腕がぁぁぁ！
My arm!
力の入れ方ってものを教えてやる。
I'll teach you how to put strength into it!
怖い怖い、やめてください！
Scary, please stop!
莉々華、大丈夫？動く？大丈夫です、動けました。
Ririka, you okay? Can you move? I'm fine, I shook it off.
よかった、もうちょっとで壊すところでしたね。
Good, I was close to breaking you.
本当にホロメンは、あの力の弱い子が多いので、僕がね、おかしいような雰囲気がよく漂いますが、
Truly, most Hololive members are physically weak, which is why I might seem a bit unusual.
まあそしてそんなね、あのキャラとツッコミキャラ、大きなターニングポイントとなりました。
And so, that character and my "tsukkomi" role became a huge turning point for me.
で、このツッコミキャラなんですけど、当時マインクラフトのホロライブサーバー内に、かなた城をお城をね、建設していた僕なんですが、
Regarding my tsukkomi role, back when I was building "Kanata Castle" on the Minecraft Hololive server,
それを見たフレア先輩が、「かなた学校建設予定地」とね、看板を書きまして、学校に見えたんですよね。
Flare-senpai saw it and put up a sign that said "Kanata School Construction Site," making it look like a school.
「学校じゃねーからこれ！」と、思わず言ったと。
"This isn't a school!!" I instinctively retorted.
そしてみこ先輩も来て、「AO入学可能」と。
Then Miko-senpai showed up and added, "AO admissions available!"
で、学校いじりのボケが続いたので「学校じゃねーよ」とね、ツッコミ続けたと。
And since the school joke kept going, I kept shouting, "This isn't a school!!"
いいよいいよ。
That's fine, whatever!
で、リスナーも喜んでくれまして、この時に気づいたことがあります。
And the listeners loved it too, which made me realize something right then.
次のページ。ホロライブにはボケが多い！
Hololive has way too many bokes!
分かる〜！
So true!
ボケ属性のホロメンが非常に多いんですよ
There are so many boke-attribute members in Hololive.
僕はこうなります 次のページ
So I ended up like this. Next page.
クセつよだらけのhololive「ツッコミ属性」に一筋の光！
A ray of light for Hololive's eccentric tsukkomi attribute!
おー
Oooh!
そうなんです。僕はここからツッコミについて学び出します
That's right. From here on, I started learning about tsukkomi.
真面目に学び出しましてね、あの、ま、ちゃんとツッコミできるようになったらすごい役割的にもいいのかなと思って
I started studying it seriously... I thought if I could properly do tsukkomi, it would be great role-wise.
あのテレビを見て参考にしたツッコミ芸人の方がいらっしゃいます。その方がこちら次のページ
So there's a tsukkomi comedian I referenced by watching TV. That person is... on the next page.
くりぃむしちゅー 上田晋也
Cream Stew's Shinya Ueda
確かに確かに。ツッコミだよね
So true, so true. Definitely a tsukkomi.
あのしゃべくりとかを見て面白いなと思って、上田さんを参考にツッコミを勉強しました
I watched Shabekuri and thought it was funny, so I studied tsukkomi by referencing Ueda-san.
例えツッコミが多くて、あの、すごく難しいんですけど、あんな風になりたいと思いながら勉強いたしました
He uses a lot of analogical tsukkomi, which is very hard, but I studied wishing I could be like that.
元々一方的に喋ってしまうオウム返しするみたいなことがあったけど
Originally, I used to just talk one-sidedly or just parrot things back,
ツッコミを意識してからはしっかり相手の言葉を聞いたりとか待つこともできるようになりました
but after being conscious of tsukkomi, I became able to listen properly to the other person's words and wait.
すごーい！素晴らしい！感動！
Amazing! Wonderful! So moving!
そして僕はツッコミで自分のポジションを開拓していくこととなります
And so, I would carve out my own position with tsukkomi.
ここまでの教訓としましては、次のページ
As the lesson up to this point... next page.
自然とキャラはついてくる！焦って無理しても空回りするだけ
Your character naturally comes to you! Rushing or forcing it just makes you spin your wheels.
なるほど
I see.
無理してキャラ付けしなくても勝手についいていってそのほうが自分も楽だと
Even without forcing a persona, it naturally follows and it's easier for yourself,
配信の中でね、自然と自分に合ったキャラがついてくるのでね、焦らず、ホロメンと喋ったりとか、配信のねやり方、いいやり方を見つけるのがいいんじゃないかなと思います
so in streams, a natural persona suited for you will follow, so don't rush, talk with Holomem, and find a good streaming style.
やっぱキャラをどうしようとか自分の理想もあるし求められるものの違いとかあると思うんだけど
You might have your own ideal persona or wonder what's expected of you,
一番やりやすいのが、日々ね配信をたくさんするので絶対いいです。今キャラ無いとか思ってもいつか絶対ついていくから、本当にね、大丈夫ですと
but the easiest way is doing lots of streams every day, that's definitely best. Even if you think you have no persona now, it will definitely follow eventually, so really, it's okay.
この配信マジで、あの、全ホロライブの新人に見せる会やったほうがいいですマジでマジで！
This stream seriously... we should totally make all new Hololive members watch this session, seriously!
ないないよ、まずね入ったらこの配信を見てもらう、とりあえず見ろつって
No way, first when they enter they watch this stream, just telling them 'watch this first'
という感じで配信にも慣れていった僕ですが、もともとhololiveに入ってやりたかったことがありました。次のページ
So as I got used to streaming, there was something I originally wanted to do when I entered Hololive. Next page.
hololiveでやりたかったこと 歌
Things I wanted to do in Hololive: Singing
イメージある。ありがとうございます
We have that image. Thank you very much.
子供の頃からアイドルに憧れ続けおりまして
Ever since I was a child, I've continued to admire idols,
あのパワーポイントデビュー配信でもライブでコール＆レスポンスするのが目標と言っていたりします
and even in my PowerPoint debut stream, I said my goal was to do call & response at a live concert.
ただ当時は明確な目標はなく、ま、いつかソロライブできたらなっていう感じだったし、そんなすぐにとは思ってなかったですと
However, back then I didn't have a clear goal, just hoping to do a solo concert someday, and I didn't think it would be so soon.
歌が好きな僕は2020年の7月ぐらいから月曜日の夜に毎週歌枠をやってました
As someone who loves singing, around July 2020 I started doing weekly singing streams on Monday nights.
いろんな方に歌聴いて欲しいとか歌上手くなりたいとかまあそういうことをやってたので自分でもすごく楽しみにしていた歌枠だったんですけど
I wanted various people to listen to my singing and wanted to get better, so I was really looking forward to those singing streams, but...
そんな僕に異変が起きます
An abnormality happens to me.
耳の持病が悪化
My chronic ear condition worsened.
そうなんです
That's right.
え、これどんな症状だったんでしたっけ？
Eh, what kind of symptoms were those again?
これはね、あの、まあもともとデビュー前からちょっと高い音が聞こにくいとかあと低音が聞こにくいとか色々あったんですけど
Well, originally even before debut, I had trouble hearing high notes, or low notes, various things,
この頃はちょっと悪化しまして片方の耳はほぼ聞こえてない
but around this time it worsened, and one ear became almost completely deaf.
聞こえてないけど常に耳鳴りがいつもしてたり、何かの特定の音が割れて聞こえるような状態になっておりまして
Though I couldn't hear, I constantly had tinnitus, and certain specific sounds started sounding distorted and cracked,
耳が聞こえづらいと歌にどんな影響が出てしまうのか？次のページ
and when your ears are hard of hearing, what kind of impact does it have on singing? Next page.
自分の歌声がわからない
Not knowing my own singing voice
なんかね、自分が歌ってる音程もちょっとずれて聞こえる時があるし
Sometimes the pitch I'm singing sounds a bit off to me,
声の大きさがわからなくて、なんか大きく出しちゃうんだよね、力んじゃうとか
and I don't know the volume of my voice, so I end up projecting it too loudly or straining.
うまく歌えなくてすごくこう、難しい
I can't sing well and it's very difficult.
となると、ま、あれだけ好きだった歌が嫌いになってくるんですよ。うまく歌えないなってなって歌わないと、咽の筋肉も終わっていきどんどん下手になってあーもう嫌だと
So, songs that I loved so much started becoming something I hated. Thinking I can't sing well, if I don't sing, the throat muscles atrophy, I get worse and worse, and I think 'ugh, I hate this.'
そしてまあお医者さんからも1回ね、お休みした方がいいんじゃないかとと言われた結果、次のページ
And well, the doctor also suggested I should take a break once. As a result... next page.
毎週やっていた歌枠が終了
Weekly singing streams ended
悲しいよ
So sad...
ちょっとここはね、悲しいとこなんですけど、すごい悲しかったですね
That part is sad, it was really sad.
歌にハンデがあるっていうのはしょうがないとは思いつつ、なんでこうい自分なのかなっていうふうに落ち込んだ時期もありました
While thinking having a handicap in singing can't be helped, there were times I felt depressed wondering why it had to be me.
が、しかしそんな時に支えになったのがこちら！次のページ
However, what supported me at that time was... this! Next page.
辛い時に支えになったもの リスナーの温かい言葉と仲間のホロメン
What supported me during hard times: Warm words from listeners and fellow Holomem
あったかーい
So warm...
やっぱりみんなに支えてもらって、時間がかかってもしっかり頑張ろうかって思えてきまして、どんどん上がっていきましたね、モチベーション
Knowing everyone supported me, I felt like 'even if it takes time, I'll do my best,' and my motivation steadily went up.
よかったー！
That's great!
もう一番大好きな音楽が嫌いになって、趣味が1個なくなったって思ってたんですけど
I thought my favorite music had become something I hated and I lost one of my hobbies, but...
リスナーさんからは「それでも歌大好きだよ」って
When listeners tell me, "Even so, I love your singing,"
言ってもらえて、まだやっててもいいのかなとか
and that it's okay for me to keep going,
思えましたし、
it makes me think...
そういうふうに今絶対聞き苦しいのに聞いてくれるみんなのために頑張りたいと思いましたね、心から。
And from the bottom of my heart, I want to work hard for everyone who listens to me even now when it's hard to listen to.
やっぱりリスナーさんからのさ、温かい言葉ってさ、心に残るし嬉しいよね。
Warm words from listeners really stay in your heart and make you happy, don't they?
嬉しい。そうだよね。
They're so happy. That's right.
みんなあるよね、そういうことね。
Everyone experiences that kind of thing.
めっちゃあります。なんかちょっとやっぱ落ち込んだ時とかにエゴサして、
We definitely do. Sometimes when I'm feeling down, I vanity-search...
「今日も可愛かったな」とか
and see things like, "You were so cute today," or
「いっぱい頑張ってるね」とか、
"You're working really hard."
そういう優しいコメント見るだけでも胸がいっぱいになって、また頑張ろうって気持ちにマジでなれます。
Just seeing those gentle comments fills my heart, and it genuinely makes me feel like I can try hard again.
ありがとう。
Thank you.
ありがとう。そうだよね。
Thank you. That's so true.
ラミィも自分の体調の悪化で配信がしばらくできなかった時期があるんだけど、
I also had a period where I couldn't stream for a while due to my health deteriorating,
その間にリスナーさんがずっと「ラミィちゃんいつまでも待ってるからね」って、
and during that time, listeners constantly told me, "Lamy-chan, we'll wait for you forever, so..."
「体調よく直すようにちゃんと今休んだんだよ」って、
"Make sure you rest properly right now so you can recover fully."
ずっと待っててくれて、
They kept waiting for me.
実際復帰した時もみんな温かく「ラミィちゃん待ってたよ、良かったね」って迎え入れてくれて、
And when I actually returned, everyone warmly welcomed me back, saying, "We waited for you, Lamy-chan, I'm so glad."
「リスナーさんあの時はありがとう。雪民さんいつも大好きだよ。」
"Listeners, thank you for back then. Yukimin, I always love you."
えー、エモい。
Aww, so emotional.
おかゆ先輩もありますか？
Okayu-senpai, do you have any experiences like that?
おかゆ先輩は体調崩したこととかはないけど、
I haven't really ruined my health or anything, but
やっぱりこうゲームやっててめっちゃ悲しいシーンが来て、もうエンエン泣いちゃったりして鼻ずっぴずびになったりするんだけど、
when I'm playing games and a really sad scene comes up, I end up crying my eyes out with a stuffy nose.
「ゆっくりでいいよ」「ゆっくり鼻かんでいいよ」って
But people say things like, "Take your time," "Take your time blowing your nose,"
言ってくれる優しさを感じますね、いつも本当に。
and I really feel their kindness every time.
ありがとうね。
Thank you.
優し、優しいね。
So kind, so kind.
あと、たくさんねホロメンにも応援してもらって、例えばフレア先輩から耳の病気とかハンデがあってもその上でも歌上手だからすごいよって言ってもらったりして、勇気づけられたりとか。
Also, I received support from many Hololive members. For instance, Flare-senpai encouraged me, saying, "Even with ear illnesses or handicaps, you're amazing because you're such a great singer."
あとは同期の桐生ココというね、あの人がいたんですけども、まあ今卒業してしまいましたが、
And then there was my generation mate, Kiryu Coco. She has already graduated,
当時一緒の家で同居していたので、僕が落ち込んでいる時、
but back then we lived together in the same house. When I was feeling down,
特に何か言うわけでもなく、「あ、飯食う？」みたいな感じで、
rather than saying anything in particular, she'd be like, "Ah, wanna eat?"
ちょっと一緒にね、なんかあの味噌汁食べたりとか、
We'd eat miso soup together,
午前3時におやつ食べたりとか、
or eat snacks at 3 AM.
そういうのができたのが今思うとすごく助かりました。
Looking back, being able to do things like that was such a huge help.
そんな時に大事件が起きます。
At that time, a major incident occurs.
次のページ、同期メンバーの「卒業」です。
The next page: the "graduation" of a generation member.
これはですね、あの4期生はもともと今4人なんですけど、5人おりまして、
You see, the 4th generation originally had 5 members instead of 4 like now.
あの同期の本当天才のように面白かった桐生ココがですね、卒業することになりました。
Kiryu Coco, who was ridiculously funny like a genius among our peers, decided to graduate.
まあなにより同居とかしてたりとか生活共 にしたりっていうのもあって、いろんな話も聞いていたし仲も本当一番よかったかなと思います。
More than anything, since we lived together and shared our lives, I heard a lot from her, and I think we were truly the closest.
その時に活動の先に求めるものとか生活の感じとかも色々似ていて、本当に気が合ったというか、
At that time, what we sought in our activities and our lifestyle were quite similar, so we really clicked.
そんなココの卒業っていうのは僕にとってもかなり大きい出来事でございました。
Coco's graduation was a tremendously big event for me as well.
でね、莉々華はだって喋ったことないもんね。
And Ririka hasn't even spoken with her, right?
そうですね、もう莉々華が入った時にはもうすでにご卒業されてたんですけど、でもやっぱ伝説のドラゴンのイメージがすごくて、もう最強の人っていうイメージがあります。
That's right, she had already graduated by the time Ririka joined. But the image of the legendary dragon is so strong, she feels like the strongest person ever.
いや、そうだよ、もうね僕たちまココちゃんとかかなたんの前から入ってるメンバーから見ても、やっぱココちゃんはすごい伝説を残していったなっていう印象はありますよ。
Exactly. Even for members like us who joined before Coco-chan and Kanata, the impression is that Coco-chan left behind incredible legends.
そうなんですよ。その4期生がねホロライブに入って、ARKとかねあさココとかも毎日胸がドキドキするような時期だったし、
Exactly. When the 4th generation joined Hololive, with things like ARK and AsaCoco, it was a time when our hearts throbbed every single day.
毎日の朝のライブ配信とか、そのほかのホロメンの情報をまとめてニュースでやるっていうのがすごく斬新で、
Doing daily morning live streams and wrapping up news about other Hololive members was so groundbreaking.
そうだね。天才だったなって。
That's right. She was a genius.
本当そうですよね。準備とかも大変な中そういうこともやって、まああの箱のためになったらいいとすごく考える人でしたね。
Truly. Even amidst difficult preparations, she did all that, and she was someone who constantly thought about what would benefit the whole agency.
そんなふうに仲がよかったからこそ、卒業が完全に決まった時は、まあやっぱり悲しい気持ちはもちろんありました。
Precisely because we were so close, when her graduation was fully decided, of course I felt a sense of sadness.
で、その時にねココの卒業を聞いた僕は最後にやりたかったことがありました。それがこちら次のページ。
And when I heard about Coco's graduation, there was something I wanted to do one last time. That is this—next page.
4期生としてのオリジナル楽曲。
An original song as the 4th generation.
やっぱりせっかくなら5人のオリジナル曲欲しいよなって思ったんですよね。
I thought, if possible, we'd really want an original song with all 5 of us.
そこです運営さんに4期生の曲作りたいと言うとこう言われます。次のページ。
When I told management we wanted to make a 4th gen song, they told me this—next page.
「間に合いません。」
"We won't make it in time."
そうなんですね。曲の制作には時間かかりますし、卒業が決まった時にはもう今からの楽曲制作は間に合わないとはっきり言われました。
That's right. Producing a song takes time, and when the graduation was decided, they clearly told me there wasn't enough time to start producing a new song now.
そしてこれを言われた僕はこう思います。次のページ。
And upon hearing that, I thought this—next page.
「だったら自分で作っちゃおう。」
"Then I'll just make it myself!"
発注すると間に合わないなら
If ordering it wouldn't make it in time...
If ordering wouldn't make it in time,
自分で作れば間に合うだろうと思って
I figured I could make it myself in time,
初めての作詞作曲をします
so I did my very first lyrics and composition.
こうしてできた楽曲が次のページ
The song created this way is on the next page.
4期生5人で歌う 最初で最後のオリジナル楽曲『キセキ結び』となります
It's our first and last original song sung by all five 4th generation members, "Kiseki Musubi".
当時の僕が思いを込めて いろんな方に協力をしていただいて発表することができました
Putting my feelings from back then into it, with the cooperation of many people, I was able to announce it.
映像があるのでご覧ください
Please take a look at the video.
約束しようよ 僕ら出会えたキセキ
Let's make a promise, the miracle of meeting you
忘れないように
So we'll never forget...
夢抱いて集う 青春アニメみたいな
Gathered with dreams, like a coming-of-age anime
ハッピーエンドになる 彼方へ飛ぶよ
We fly toward the horizon for a happy ending
寝ぼけ目 あくびして 今日は何をしようか?
Rubbing sleepy eyes and yawning, what should we do today?
永久に続く海を駆け抜ける
Running through the sea that stretches on forever
今はため息よりも勇気を
Now, more than sighs, let's take courage
諦めるなんてないの
There's no giving up
ここで歌う
Singing right here
僕の声は聞こえてますか? きみに届け!
Can you hear my voice? Reaching out to you!
学校の友達じゃきっとない出会いだった
An encounter unlike any school friends could bring
画面の先の遥か遠くまで
Far away beyond the screen
ささくれた言葉も誰かの笑顔になれる
Even rough words can become someone's smile
それぞれの色で星結ぶキセキ
A miracle tying stars together in our respective colors
キラキラ輝くステージに 連れてくよ
We'll take you to a sparkling, shining stage
...
はい、ありがとうございますー！
Yes, thank you very much!
めっちゃよかったー！
That was so good!
ありがとうございましたー！
Thank you very much!
いやもう本当にね、これメロディも歌も良くて、
Seriously though, both the melody and lyrics are great,
この曲を作っていた当時 おかゆ先輩とめっちゃ遊んでて
And back when she was making this song, she hung out with Okayu-senpai a lot,
めっちゃ遊んでた！マジで毎日会ってたよね
We hung out so much! We genuinely met every day, right?
その時かなたが「僕今作詞頑張ってて」って言っててさ
And at that time, Kanata said, "I'm working hard on the lyrics right now,"
完成した曲がさ、こんないい曲だから
And the completed song was such a wonderful song,
すっごい褒めてくれて
She praised me so much.
歌詞の中にみんなの名前入ってて、もうエモエモすぎんか?
Everyone's names are in the lyrics, isn't that way too emotional?
いや本当そうなんです
Yeah, it really is.
天才でしょ? これ
She's a genius, right?
いろんな人に助していただいて、こうして公開することができたんですが
I was helped by so many people, and that's how I was able to release it, but
悲しんだりとか寂しがってるだけではいけないかなと、僕思いました
I felt that just being sad or lonely wouldn't do.
この頃の人生グラフはこうなっております。次のページ。
My life graph around this time looks like this. Next page.
上がってきたー！上がった！上がってきた！
It went up! It went up! It went up!
周りと比較するより過去の自分と比較するっていうのが一番いいよねみたいな話をよくここともしていまして
I often talked about how comparing yourself to your past self is better than comparing yourself to others around you,
そういうことを続けて、とにかく自分を磨いていこうと思いました
and I thought I should keep doing that and keep polishing myself.
改めて歌に力を入れていくんですが、ソロライブをやにするにはどうすればいいか?っていうのを考えた時に
And then, I started putting more effort into singing again, and when I thought about how to do a solo live,
まずは天音かなた＝歌っていう印象をつけようと思いました
First, I wanted to create the impression of "Amane Kanata = Singing."
そのために意識していたことがあります。それが次のページ。
To achieve that, there was something I was conscious of. That is the next page.
他のメンバーのライブにいっぱいゲストで出演させていただく
Appearing as a guest in many other members' lives.
当時記念ライブにはホロメンをゲストで呼ぶのが当たり前の時代だったので
At that time, calling Holomem as guests for commemorative lives was the norm,
いただいたオファーも本当にありがたい機会で、もちろん祝う気持ちが1番なんですけど、自分がいっぱい歌いたいという思いで引き受けていきました
and the offers I received were truly appreciated opportunities. Of course celebrating was my top priority, but with the desire to sing a lot, I accepted them.
さらに、こんなことをしてみました。次のページ。
Furthermore, I tried doing something like this. Next page.
2周年記念LIVEでゲストなしのソロライブ。おおすごーい！
Solo live without guests at the 2nd Anniversary LIVE. Oh, amazing!
この自分のデビュー2周年記念ライブの「リベンジ」というものでは、ゲストがいるのが当たり前の時代になっておりまして
In this "Revenge" live for my 2nd debut anniversary, having guests had become the standard,
ソロライブをする人がいなくなってて、あえてゲストを呼ばず1時間で15曲も歌うライブを挑戦的にやってみたりもしました
and solo lives had disappeared, but I dared to try doing a solo live without guests, singing as many as 15 songs in an hour in a challenging way.
この頃から自分の歌についても真剣に向き合うようになっていくんですが
So from around this time, I started facing my own singing seriously, but
僕は一から発声や歌い方を見直すことになります
I ended up reviewing my vocalization and singing style from scratch.
ここでやったことがこちら次のページ。
What I did here is on the next page.
自分の歌い方の「癖」の選別、人気曲のボーカルだけを抽出して分析、昔の歌の研究
Discriminating the "habits" of my singing style, extracting and analyzing only vocals of popular songs, researching old songs.
と、いうのをね、やりました
I did those things.
この癖なんですけど、
As for these habits,
強い癖が個性があっていいとか癖がないほうが聞きやすいよとかあったんですけど、
some say strong habits give personality, while others prefer none for easier listening,
まずは自分はやっぱり癖はどちらかというと強いから、じゃあどこを残そうかと考えた時に、
but since my habits tend to be quite strong, when deciding what to keep—
まずは癖をゼロにしようと思いまして、
I first decided to try reducing my habits to zero.
あのちょうど歌ってみたの「炉心融解」とかボーカロイドの曲歌ったんですけど、その時も癖ゼロでボカロみたいに歌うことを意識したりしました。
For example, when I sang Vocaloid songs like "Meltdown" for covers, I consciously aimed for zero habits and sang like a Vocaloid.
いい癖は残して、ちょっと聞きにくいなっていう癖はなるべくなくすっていうことでちょっとブラッシュアップしていこうと思ってましてね。
So the idea was to keep good habits, get rid of awkward ones as much as possible, and polish my style.
ででも思った。一時期の時からかなたんの歌い方変わったなって思った。
But you know, I thought, "Kanatan's singing style changed at some point."
いやそうなんです。おかえり先輩ともね、いっぱい歌ってみたね歌わせていただいたりしてるんですけど、
That's right! I've sung many cover songs with Okayu-senpai,
その初期の頃歌ってみたやってる時はまだ選別前で（声が）ちょっとブスの時（ちょいブスの時ね）その、まあそんなこともあった。
but back in the early days before I filtered them out, my voice had some awkward moments—well, those kind of things happened too.
みたいな感じで、ただこれは結構辛い作業で、これは実は1年かかりまして、選びましたね。
Like that. But it was quite a painful process that actually took a year to sort out.
であと人気の曲、ま例えばあのYOASOBIさんとか流行りのアーティスト、やっぱ流行りの歌い方っていうものがあるなっていうのを 感じて、あのそういう方々のボーカルを聞いて、こういう癖は入れるけどここには入れないんだとか、研究というか分析しましたね。
And for popular songs—like YOASOBI and other trendy artists—I felt there's a certain trendy way of singing. So I listened to their vocals and analyzed things like "you can put this habit here, but not there"—it was more of a study or analysis.
いや流行りがありつつもそこに寄せるか寄せまいかっていうのはすごくね、考えましたね。
Even with trends, I thought a lot about whether or not to lean into them.
であとは昔の歌も研究して、曲にもこう流行りの周期があって、曲のなんかこうロックっぽいのが流行ったり、バラードが流行ったりとか、今こうちょっとエモ系だったり、昔流行った曲とかその時に流行ってる歌い方とかもかなり研究を…
And I also researched older songs. Songs go through trend cycles—sometimes rock is popular, sometimes ballads, or nowadays, emo-style. I heavily researched past hits and the singing styles of those eras...
え～すごい。なんかさっきツッコミもそのいろいろ勉強されてたみたいな話もあったし、 今回もこういろいろ研究して、本当に努力家というか…
Wow. Earlier we heard how she studied tsukkomi routines, and now she's researching all this too—she's really such a hard worker...
おいはおまえ…！ありがと120点のコメント！
Hey, you...! Thanks for the 120-point comment!
で、まあとにかくこれほどしないと自分の、まあ耳の癖もありますし、ちょっと聞きづらくなってり歌っていうのが、なかなか変えられないなってことでイチからやろうと思って、
Anyway, if I didn't go this far, due to my own biased listening and hard-to-change awkward singing habits, I wouldn't be able to fix them, so I decided to start from scratch.
これをやった結果、昔3時間かかっていたレコーディングが今は20分くらいで終わるようになりました！
As a result of doing this, recordings that used to take 3 hours now finish in about 20 minutes!
すご～い！はや～！ありがとうございます！
Amazing! That's so fast! Thank you!
ま、これもね、レコーディングをやる時にこの癖を入れたいなって言って何度も何度も試すとかやってたんですけど、それがパッとできるようになったって、納得できる歌い方ができるようになったっていう感じでしたね。
Well, when recording, I used to test over and over wanting to add certain habits, but now I can do it instantly and achieve the singing style I'm satisfied with.
みなさんはレコーディングにこだわりってありますか？
Do you guys have any specific preferences or habits when recording?
こだわりというか、今現在まさに自分の癖で悩んでて、そうなんだ。なんか歌って今までやってこなかったんだけど、このライブに入って歌を歌う機会がすごく増えて、初めて自分の癖みたいなのが出てきちゃってるの。
Preference? Well, right now I'm actually struggling with my own habits. You see, I hadn't really sung much before, but since joining hololive, opportunities to sing have increased so much that my own habits are starting to show for the first time.
逆にそれを残したほうがいいのか、はぶいてもっとまっさらな歌い方にしたらいいのか、すごい今リアルタイムで悩んでて、この件かたなんに相談します。
Strangely enough, I'm struggling in real-time with whether I should keep these habits or strip them away for a cleaner style, so I'm consulting Kanatan about this.
待ってます！相談するの、続きあるからね。
I'm waiting! There's more to this consultation, you know.
ふたりは？あ、デリカは、なんか感情が死んでるのか分かんないんですけど…
What about you two? Ah, as for Lamy—wait, I mean, sometimes I can't tell if her emotions are dead...
どういうこと！？感情が死んでるのか分かんない
What do you mean?! You can't tell if my emotions are dead?!
歌う時にやっぱ感情を乗せるっていうのがあんまり得意じゃなくて、その歌詞の意味とかが頭をこうスーッて通り抜けちゃうんですよね。
When I sing, I'm not very good at putting emotion into it, so the meaning of the lyrics tends to just slip right through my head.
なるべくどういう情景かとかを思い描きながら歌うように頑張ってるんで…
I try my best to sing while picturing the scene as much as possible,
まずはね、ちょっと感情を取り戻すところから…
so first of all, I need to start by getting my emotions back...
元々なくなってる。化け物かもしれない。
They're gone from the start. Might be a monster.
そんなことないよ！そんなことないよ！
No way! That's not true!
おかゆ先輩感情入れて歌うの得意な気がしますけど。めちゃめちゃ得意。本当。
Okayu-senpai seems good at putting emotion into her singing. Super good at it. Really.
僕とかかなたんってさ、ミックスの勉強もしてたことあったじゃん。
Back then, Kanatan and I also studied mixing, right?
だからこうミックスするとどうしても表情感って消えやすい、ピッチの補正でね、補正で消えるんだよ。
So when you mix, emotional nuance tends to get lost due to pitch correction—it gets wiped out by correction.
だからそのピッチを取るか表現を取るか考えること多いかもね。
So you often have to weigh whether to prioritize pitch accuracy or emotional expression.
いや本当、大事やな。
That's so true, really important.
そうだね。なんか音程を気にすると表情が落ちていくっていうのは絶対あるから、
Exactly. If you worry too much about pitch, your facial expression and emotion definitely drop.
1個だけこの1行めっちゃいいからここだけ入れようとか決めるとやりやすいかも。
So deciding "this one line is super good, so I'll just put emotion here" makes it easier.
めっちゃ勉強になる！タメになる～！
Super educational! So helpful~!
と言いつつ、まあ僕もまだまだなんだが、こういったね地道な活動の結果、2022年の年末に行われた3周年記念ライブ「別世界」ではこうなります。次のページ。
That said, I still have a long way to go, but as a result of these steady efforts, here's how it turned out at my 3rd-anniversary live "Bessekai" at the end of 2022. Next page.
21秒のロングトーン歌が大反響！すご～い！すごいんだから。本当にすごい。
Her 21-second long-tone singing became a massive sensation! Amazing! She's really amazing. Truly amazing.
このライブの、ロングトーン部分の映像があるみたいなので
There seems to be footage of the long-tone part of this live,
ご覧ください。よろしければご覧ください、どうぞ！
so please take a look. Here you go!
ショートとかでもめっちゃ流れてくるからね。
It shows up everywhere in Shorts, you know.
そうなんだよ。
That's right.
そうそう。
Yeah, yeah.
僕じゃない人がショートたくさん切り抜いてるんだけど。
People who aren't me are clipping so many Shorts of it.
すごいからね。
It's amazing.
脅威の…みたいな。
Like a menace...
何回も見たいここ。
I want to watch this over and over.
やばいもう息した？
Oh no, did you breathe yet?
そう息した息した
Yeah, I breathed.
まだまだ苦しいまだ苦しい
Still painful!
ノド苦しいノド苦しい
My throat hurts!
ここから上がるのがすごいよ
Rising from here is amazing!
本当にそう。上がるってなるからね。
Really. It's like, it goes up!
どうやって？マジでやばい。
How? Seriously insane.
で、最後のビブラートね。
And then the final vibrato.
うん。
Yeah.
まだ残ってたんかってなる。
Makes you go, "There was still some left?!"
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
すごい技術だよ。
That's an amazing technique.
いやいやいや、本当にねとんでもなく練習したんですけども。
No, no, I really practiced like crazy.
あの、これは実は元をたどると、ちょっと逃げのロングトーンで。
Actually, if you trace the origin, it's a bit of a cop-out long tone.
ええ！？ええ！？なぜ逃げだったかというと、
What?! Why was it a cop-out, you ask?
どこに逃げたの？
Where did you run away to?
あの、この「unravel」という楽曲、ここでデスボイスが本家だと、ゥーって出るの。
In the song "unravel", the original has a death voice part...
それができないんでロングトーンにした。
Since I couldn't do that, I made it a long tone.
ええ！？というのが実は始まりだったんです。
What?! That's actually how it started.
逃げではない！逃げない挑戦だよ！デスボイスが逃げてきて、
It's not running away! It's an unflinching challenge!
で、ロングトーンとなったんですが、ま、当時ね、
And it became a long tone, but back then...
やりたいことをかなり詰め込んだライブが成功して、100万人記念の新衣装も見せるタイミングだったり、
The live packed with everything I wanted to do succeeded, showing off my 1M milestone outfit.
が、unravelでねロングトーンしたことを、あの色んな人に本当にと思った以上にいろんな方にね見ていただいて、「今までで1番ライブよかった！」っていう、
So many people watched my long tone in unravel and gave me amazing feedback.
反響をいただいたりとか、「歌上手くなったね」って言ってもらえるのがすごく嬉しくて、まだ頑張っていこうと思いました。
Hearing things like "You've improved!" made me want to keep trying.
この時の反響がなければ、もう自分はね、必死に歌頑張るということはなかったかなと、思います。
Without that response, I wouldn't be working this hard at singing.
で、そのあとね、え、去年3月に、天音かなたファーストアルバムCDの「Unknown DIVA」を発表することもできまして、見事完売できまして、
And last March, I released my 1st album "Unknown DIVA", which sold out brilliantly!
本当に。運営さんもね、頑張ったと認めてくれたって感じましたし、
I felt like management acknowledged my hard work.
ま、何より聞いたね、あの、へ民の皆さんが嬉しそうにしてくれたり、好きな曲を発見してくれたりして、僕もすごく嬉しかったです。
Above all, seeing the fans look so happy made me so glad.
そしてなんと！今年7月23日には、セカンドアルバム「Trigger」を発売します！さらにさらに、
And what's more! On July 23rd, my 2nd album "Trigger" releases!
8月13日は、待望のソロライブを行わせていただく運びとなりました！
And on August 13th, my long-awaited solo live will finally happen!
おめでと～！ありがとうございます！
Congratulations~! Thank you very much!
でもこのアルバムのTriggerは、ジャケットとかアナザージャケットっていうのを自分で発注からやって、クオリティにこだわっていたりとか。
For "Trigger", I handled ordering the jackets myself and was very particular about quality.
楽曲なんですけど、「十万億土」という楽曲を作詞作曲してみました。こちらもね、ラップを入れてみたり挑戦してみたので是非チェックして欲しいです。
I also wrote/composed a track called "Jumangokudo" featuring rap, so please check it out.
めちゃ楽しみ〜！
I'm so excited!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
他にも「世界で一番のアイドル」という楽曲の作詞もしまして、
I also wrote lyrics for a song called "The Number One Idol in the World".
こちらはですね、あの先ほどの十万億土とは全く違く、もう素直な気持ちを、韻などは踏んでおりません！素直な気持ちを文字にしたので、応援してくれるへ民に届いたらいいなと思っておりました。
Unlike the previous song, this has no rhymes—just my sincere feelings hoping to reach my fans.
絶対届くよ！
It'll definitely reach us!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
全体的に歌がパワーアップしていると思いますので、ソロライブも楽しみにしていてほしいと思います！
I think my singing has leveled up overall, so look forward to the solo live!
現在のhololive人生グラフはこうなります。次のページ！
Here is my Hololive life graph. Next page!
おおーー上がってる！上昇してる〜！
Whoa, it's going up! It's rising!
現在右肩上がりで順調にこさせていただいております。
It has been steadily climbing upward.
そしても、これもこれもね、ここに集まってくれた3人に本当に心から感謝している。
I truly, from the bottom of my heart, thank the three of you here today.
きてもらって お忙しい中。
Taking time out of your busy schedules...
カニが待っているからな。
Because crab is waiting.
カニ食べたい〜！カニ食べたい〜！
I want to eat crab~!
奢りたいと思います。
I'd love to treat you.
で、最後に僕のデビュー配信を振り返らせていただきますが、僕はデビュー配信でこんなことを言っていました。こちら。
Finally, let's look back at my debut stream. Here's what I said back then.
なんかさ、僕が初配信でこうやっていっぱい話したさ、
You know, back when I talked so much in my debut stream,
あの、突拍もない夢をいつか叶えることができたらさ、
if I could someday make those outrageous dreams come true,
それはまず、まず、あのリスナーさん、へ民の皆のおかげだから、
that would first be thanks to the listeners and all the Heimin.
こうしてね、活動が始まったけど、最初から最後まで頑張って自分も皆も今より幸せになるようにって、
Working hard from start to finish so everyone can be happier than before—
それが天音かなたがVTuberとして活動する理由です。
that is why Amane Kanata is active as a VTuber.
これ、初配信でしての？いや、すごいよ、初配信でしっかりしてる〜！
Did she say that in her debut stream?! Wow, she's so put-together!
あのね、当時は突拍もない夢だと思ってましたけど、本当にいろんな夢が叶うところまでこられたね。やっと。
I thought they were outrageous dreams, but I've made it to where they're coming true.
すごい！
Amazing!
ということで、いろんなしくじりや事件があって紆余曲折しましたが、
So, after various blunders, incidents, and many twists and turns,
今こうして天音かなたという僕、出来上がりました！ありがとうございました！
and now, Amane Kanata is complete! Thank you very much!
今日の授業いかがだったでしょうか？
How was today's lesson?
めちゃ良かったよ
It was amazing.
超勉強になった
Super educational!
かなたんが努力の人っていうのが この時間でものすごい分かったと思う
I really understood how much of a hard worker Kanatan is during this time.
本当だよね。本当にありがと
That's so true. Thank you so much!
いろんな苦労もあっただろうに それを感じさせず
There must have been so many hardships, yet she doesn't show it at all...
いやいやいやもう本当にしてね、僕はね正直、この授業ホロメン全員分見たいぐらいあります
No, no, honestly, I'd want to see this class for every single Holomem!
みんなのこの人生を教えてくれと
Teaching us everyone's life story like this—
まあ、いうことでね、ま、歌の話もして
well, having talked about singing...
ちょっと実はね、ま、はっきり言ってこれはね、皆さん収録なんです、はっきり言って
actually, to be completely honest with you all... this is pre-recorded!
はっきり言って収録だから僕たち今、過去から来ています
To be frank, it's pre-recorded, so we're currently coming from the past!
えー未来の僕、今ここから生でね、ちょっと続きの配信してくるので
The future me is going to do the live continuation stream right now from here, so—
じゃあ、未来に行ってくる！
Well then, I'm heading to the future!
え、置いていかれる感じで？
Eh, getting left behind?
あの、僕たちはこの後どうしたら？
Um, what are we supposed to do after this?
カニ行こうな！！いぇ〜い！！カニ〜〜！
Let's go eat crab!! Yay!! Crab~~!
行ってくる〜！未来に！
I'm heading off~! To the future!
手詰まりな現状の行き場が
The dead-end current situation has nowhere to go,
とめどない感情と交差する
intersecting with endless emotions.
どうしたって変えられない
No matter what, it can't be changed;
それはきっと個人の過ちじゃない
that's surely not an individual's mistake.
救い助けが利くのは限られた範囲の話で
Salvation and help only work within a limited scope,
そこを出しゃあとは不干渉
and once you step outside that, it's non-interference.
どうせ何をしても正気がないんだって自分のどうあがこうとだって
Anyway, thinking nothing will work no matter what you do, no matter how you struggle,
びくともしない機上の風
a completely unmoving wind atop the desk.
それならこれらのことももし知らないからね
If so, even these things are things we don't know yet,
変わらない後悔があったとて
even if there are unchanging regrets,
今で切ることなんて何もないんだ
there's nothing to cut off right now.
強いどこくって責め立てない
Not blaming fiercely or cornering someone,
決まり切った実り こうすりそうもない丁寧なくり捨てても
even discarding polite things that wouldn't yield set results,
今のままもう捨てくだろ
we'll probably just throw them away as they are.
そして徐々に心が軽くなってしまう
And gradually, our hearts become lighter.
認め切れない言葉の連鎖
A chain of words I can't fully accept—
きっと僕らは無力で ああ
surely we are powerless, ah.
資料の行方が定まらないなさ
The whereabouts of the data are unsettled,
そんなにも分からないままだ
and it remains so unclear.
終わり切れない常識の尺度
The scale of endless common sense
絶対的に正しくないが
is absolutely not correct, but
僕の手におえない君の脳裏は
your mind, which is beyond my hands,
どうやったっても救いやしない
cannot be saved no matter what.
君らが自愛をこうだって
You guys ask for self-love,
正直 役目の管轄外 結局 未来の想定もセルフとなってます
honestly outside my jurisdiction; in the end, even the future's assumption is self-service.
しょうもない救済を待ってても
Even if you wait for some useless salvation,
神様も手合いはやらないし 時間が調子すぎるだけで
God won't lend a hand either, time just passes too smoothly,
とめどない思考自走を知らず
without knowing the self-propelled endless thoughts.
変わらない後悔があったとて
Even if there are unchanging regrets,
今で切ることは何も無いんだ
there is nothing to cut off right now.
強いどこくって責め立てない
Not blaming fiercely or cornering someone,
決まり切った実り こうすりそうもない住民と色々関係なく 今自分のことですいっぱいいなんだ
regardless of residents who won't yield set results, right now I'm just full of my own affairs.
みんな……！
Everyone...!
見ましたか？みんな
Did you see that, everyone?
帰ってきたよ、ちょっと。この教室で
I'm back, hold on. In this classroom—
ちょっと、一回生きて……誰もいない！
Wait, having survived once... nobody's here!
おい、勝手に帰った！
Hey, you went home without me!
いや、ありがとうございました
Well, thank you very much.
ということで、すごい高かったよね。ぱちぱちありがとう！
So, that was really high-pitched, right? Clap clap, thank you!
いま歌った曲なんですが、新曲になります！
The song I just sang is a brand new song!
こちら、7月23日水曜日に発売予定の僕のセカンドアルバム『Trigger』から、サツキさんに制作いただいた『セルフサービス』を初披露させていただきました！
We premiered "Self Service", produced by Satsuki-san, from my 2nd album "Trigger" scheduled for release on Wednesday, July 23rd!
本日このあと21時からMVを公開、そして24時から各配信サービスにて音源リリース予定です！
The MV will be released tonight after 21:00, and the audio will be released on various streaming services starting at 24:00!
そして！アルバム追加情報として、『Trigger』に収録されている全9曲の情報、
And! As additional album information, info on all 9 tracks included in "Trigger"...
初公開！
First public reveal!
今回も超豪華作家陣の皆様に素敵な全9曲を作っていただきました！
This time too, wonderful creators have made a total of 9 amazing songs for me!
アルバムはアクスタ3種セットや限定ホログラムが描かれている豪華な完全生産限定版、
The album comes in a luxurious complete production limited edition
featuring 3 acrylic stand sets and a limited hologram,
そしてABの2形態をご用意している通常版の計3種が
and the regular version with 2 types, A and B,
making 3 types in total.
大体大体大体大体！大好評と言っときますからね、みんなよろしくお願いします！
I'll say it's going to be a huge hit!
Everyone, please look forward to it!
予約受付中ですのでぜひぜひ手に入れてくださいね！
Reservations are open right now,
so please make sure to get your copy!
そしてね、YouTubeご覧の皆さまも配信画面の下にね、タグ付けされてる商品の購入ボタンから
And for those watching on YouTube, you can reserve
via the product purchase button tagged below the streaming screen
ご予約できますのでチェックしてください、絶対頑張って設定したから、多分いるはず！
so please check it out. I worked really hard
to set it up, so it should be there!
そして、皆さんお待ちかねのソロライブの追加のお知らせでございまーす！
And now, for the additional announcement
of the solo live you've all been waiting for!
まずは、おお、ありがとうございます！
First of all... oh, thank you so much!
まずはこちらの動画をどうぞ！
Please take a look at this video first!
2025.8.13
Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live
狙いを定めたその先は、あなたの心——
The target I've set my sights on is your heart—
楽曲一発一発に
Into every single song,
“僕の”感情を込めて
I pour "my" emotions
全力で撃ち抜いていく
and shoot straight through.
LOOK ON
ARIAKE ARENA
8.13 ARIAKE ARENA
一人ひとりの感情に、確かな共鳴が広がっていく
A definite resonance spreads through
each and every emotion
かっけーー！ということで今回のライブタイトルは、天音かなたファーストソロライブ「LOOK ON」です！
So cool! With that said, the title of this solo live
is Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live "LOOK ON"!
セカンドアルバム「TRIGGER」ともつながりも考えて、ライブでみんなをね、ガンガン撃ち抜いていくイメージでございます。
Thinking about its connection to the 2nd album "TRIGGER",
the image is to shoot through everyone at the live.
キービジュアルは現実世界に天界の門が降臨した、異世界感のある雰囲気になっています。
The key visual has an otherworldly atmosphere
where the gates of heaven descended onto the real world.
どうですか？このクールでかっこいい僕を見てライブへの期待感、爆上がり！
What do you think? Seeing this cool and awesome me
will skyrocket your expectations for the live!
ありたけアリーナもね、皆さんお待たせしました！会場は有明アリーナで開催いたします！
And Ariake Arena—everyone, thanks for waiting!
The venue will be Ariake Arena!
本当にね、たくさんね、偉大な先輩たちもこちらでね、ライブやってきているので、頑張ろうと思います。
So many great seniors have held concerts here too,
so I'm going to do my best.
今回のソロライブのハッシュタグはですね、「#ウチヌケカナタ」です！のんのんみんなポストして一緒にライブを盛り上げてくれー！
The hashtag for this solo live is "#UchinukeKanata"!
Everyone, please post and hype up the live together!
チケット情報はちら！S席、A席、B席の3種類をご用意しました。
Here is the ticket information!
We've prepared 3 types: S seat, A seat, and B seat.
一次先行はこのあと21時から申し込み開始となります。これね、抽選なんでみんな焦ずに大丈夫ですからね！
The first pre-order starts applications from 21:00 tonight.
It's a lottery so everyone don't panic, it's fine!
今回はチケット販売サイトのZAIKOで海外の海外向けの現実チケットを販売します！
This time, through the ticket sales site ZAIKO,
we'll sell physical tickets for overseas fans too!
世界中のね、海外に会えるの楽しみにしてるからねみんな！海外にはおら、行けないよって人も全然大丈夫！
I'm looking forward to meeting everyone around the world!
If you can't make it from overseas, it's totally fine!
配信チケットはZAIKOで販売します。こちらも21時から販売開始なので配信でね、ぜひ僕の勇姿を見に来てください！
Streaming tickets will be sold on ZAIKO. Sales also start at 21:00,
so please come watch my valiant figure on stream!
各学...間違えたわ、各座席のエリアマップはこちら！S席は1階と3階前方、A席は1階後方と2階、B席は3階後方と4階に分かれています！
Each grade... my bad, here is the area map for each seat!
S seat is 1st & front 3rd floor, A seat is 1st rear & 2nd...
おまえらいっぱいね、いっぱい来てね、散らばってくれ。
Everyone, come in droves and fill the seats.
そしてみんなお待ちかねのグッズ情報もあります！グッズはこのあと21時より販売開始するので、まずはライブに欠かせない応援セットをご紹介！
And there's also the merchandise info you've all been waiting for!
Let's first introduce the essential support set for the live!
じゃじゃーん！きちゃー！
Ta-da! It's here!
うぱおライトは見たのとおり、うぱおがモチーフになりました。おまえらもずっと欲しがってたもんね。ライブ会場うぱおで埋め尽くしましょう！
As you can see, the Upao light has Upao as its motif.
You guys have been wanting this forever. Let's fill the live venue with Upao!
Tシャツは今回のライブタイトルにある「LOOK ON」ちなんで、胸に照準マークをね、モチーフプリントしてみました。みんなのね、あの心臓、僕が思いっきり撃ち抜いてあげますので、是非展開に遊びに来てください！ライブでもぜひ来て下さい！
The T-shirt features a target mark printed on the chest related to "LOOK ON".
I'll shoot right through your hearts, so please come to the venue!
フェイスタオルはロゴを大きくあしらったデザインになっていて、これもね、弾丸で撃ち抜かれたイメージでかっこいいのね。そうですね、みんなTシャツと一緒に身につけてくれたら嬉しいなと思います。
The face towel has a bold logo design, also cool
with a bullet-pierced image. I hope you'll wear it along with the T-shirt.
セット特典のラバーバンドはクリア素材で涼しげなデザイン！ロゴが入った特別仕様なのでみんな是非ゲットして、内側にね、あの「カバー」って書いてありました！それぞれのグッズは単品でも販売します！他の先行グッズはこちら！
The rubber band in the set bonus is a cool design made of clear material!
It's a special edition with the logo—it said "COVER" inside!
じゃじゃーん！リングライトとハッピも先行発送対象となります。ハッピ欲しかったでしょ？
Ta-da! The ring light and happi coat
are also eligible for advance shipping. You wanted a happi, right?
リングライトにもね、ここを撃ち抜いてってアピールできるように標準アイコンを入れてみました！ヘー民のみんな僕がねもうどんどんおまえらを撃ち抜いていくので、是非ライブで光らせてください！
I've added a standard icon to the ring light so you can appeal
"shoot right here!" Heman folks, please make it glow at the live!
ハッピは背面に見えるキービジュアルのかなたを大きくあしらいました！
The happi coat features a large illustration
of Kanata's key visual on the back!
サイバーチックなデザインにもしてもらいましたが、
We went with a cyber-style design,
ソーラム風もちょっと浮かぶよね。
though it gives off a bit of a Solram vibe.
ヘ民のみんな、お前らは当然フル装備で応援してくれ！かなたーーっ！
Hemin everyone, of course you'll support me with full gear! Kanataaa!
リングライトとハピアーね、応援セットには実は含まれませんので、この辺ね、あの注意してくださいね。
Ring lights and happi coats aren't included in the support set, so please be careful about that.
そして、受注販売グッズはこちら！じゃじゃん！
And the made-to-order merch is right here! Ta-da!
これ、トートバッグがすごい良かったサンプル見たんですけど、
This tote bag looked amazing in the sample,
トートバッグはね、痛バッグとしても使えるように缶バッジ飾れる透明のポケットがついてて、
and it can also be used as an ita-bag with a clear pocket for badges,
キャリーケースのハンドルに通せるように通し穴もあるので、旅行の時も片手で持ち運べるですごいです、これ。
and has a pass-through for carry cases so you can carry it one-handed when traveling!
で、モチーフキーホルダーはキービジュアルの僕の首元にあるドッグタグというものをイメージしました！かっこいいデザインなので、バッグやポーチにつけてみてください。
The motif keychain is based on the dog tag around my neck in the visual! It's a cool design, so try attaching it to your bag or pouch.
アクリルスタンドもこれね、さっきビジュアルすごかった、背景の展開トラスとかなたがね、
And the acrylic stand—the visual earlier was amazing—the background truss and Kanata
別パーツになってるので、立体的に飾れてます。すごい立体感あった、もう4Dでしたね。
are separate parts, so it's displayed in 3D. It had incredible depth, practically 4D!
そしてそして、最後に注意事項です！グッズの販売期間はこの後21時から6月23日18時までです。
And finally, some important notes! The merch sales period runs from 21:00 onwards until June 23rd at 18:00.
ほんでもってみんなややこしいからね、あれなんだけど注意してほしいのが先行発送グッズはライブの前に届く予定なんですけど、
And since it's a bit confusing, please note that advance shipping merch is scheduled to arrive before the live,
受注販売グッズはライブ後！これあとなんですよ、受注販売グッズね、間違えないようにチェックしてください。
whereas made-to-order merch arrives *after* the live! Make sure not to mix them up.
ぜひよろしくお願いします。
Thank you very much.
詳しい情報は公式情報、公式X、販売サイトそして公式特設サイトをご確認ください！各時点は以上になります。
Check the official site, X, sales site, and special site for details! That concludes the items.
ということで、ソロライブはしくじらないように頑張りたいと思います。
So, I'll do my best not to mess up my solo live.
あのね、ちょっと前にさ、エプリールフールに双子の妹が登場させたりしたじゃん、
You know, a little while ago on April Fools, my twin sister appeared,
なんかあいつすごい人気になっちゃったりとかしてさ、
and she ended up getting super popular,
そういうね、ちょっといじられてないしくじりとかもいろいろあるんですけど、
and while there are various other mishaps and blunders...
ま、これからのホロライブの人生、しくじりることは確実にあると思いますが、
Well, I'm sure there will definitely be mishaps in my future Hololive life,
そんな天音かなたを、そして初めてのソロライブをよろしくお願いします！
but please support Amane Kanata, and my very first solo live!
一緒にカートに入れたらアウト分かんないあとでちょっと調べとくわみんなまた言うわ。
If you put them in the cart together... wait, I'll check later and tell you all.
ありがとうね。
Thanks.
ややこしいぞ分かる。
It's confusing, I know.
ということでね、それではみんなまたおつかなたー！ありがとう！MVに飛んでくれ！
So everyone, see you later, Otsukanata! Thank you! Go fly to the MV!